Welcome back, In this video we're going to look at another example of cool
欢迎回来，在这段视频中，我们将看到另一个很酷的例子
programing. This time let's move beyond the simple hello world kind of examples
编程。这一次，让我们超越简单的hello world之类的示例
and on to something more exciting, say, the ever popular factorial function. So,
接下来是一些更令人兴奋的事情，比如说，一直很受欢迎的阶乘函数。所以,
in order to write factorial, we'll need to open a file, which we can write some code.
为了编写阶乘，我们需要打开一个文件，我们可以编写一些代码。
Let me start that. And recall from last time that every cool program has to have a
让我开始吧。回想上一次，每个很酷的程序都必须有一个
main class and the main class is required to have a main method. And we don't care
Main类和Main类需要有Main方法。我们也不在乎
what the main method return, so we'll just have it return something a type object,
Main方法返回什么，所以我们只需要让它返回一个类型对象，
and then we'll just fill in a skeleton here on the file. And, so now we're ready
然后我们就在这份文件上填一份骨架。所以，现在我们准备好了
to write some codes. So what are we going to have the main method do? Well, before
来写一些代码。那么我们要让main方法做什么呢？嗯，在此之前
we can actually write factorially, before we can get to the guts of this program,
在我们到达这个程序的毅力之前，我们实际上可以写成事实，
which is actually not very difficult. We need to talk about IO some more. Because
这其实并不是很难。我们需要更多地讨论IO。因为
we're going to need to be able to, read and write, numbers. We need to be able to
我们需要能够读写数字。我们需要能够
read numbers from, the, the user who's running the program, and print them back
从运行该程序的用户处读取数字，并将其打印回来
out. So let's just review little bit about IO, also. In order to invoke the IO
出去。那么让我们也来回顾一下IO。为了调用IO
functions, we need an IO object. And one of the IO functions is something that
函数，我们需要一个IO对象。IO功能之一是
prints out a string. So let's just, write a program that we already know how to do,
打印出字符串。所以让我们写一个我们已经知道怎么做的程序，
just to confirm that we remember that. And, we can compile this program. And it
只是为了确认我们还记得这一点。而且，我们可以编译这个程序。而且它
should just print one. And, let's see. Indeed it does. Okay? So it prints out the
应该只打印一张。让我们看看。确实如此。好吧?所以它会打印出
number one. And so now, let's come back here and let's talk about how to do input.
一号。现在，让我们回到这里，讨论一下如何进行输入。
So, instead of just printing out the number one, let's print out a strain that
所以，与其只打印出数字1，不如打印出一个
the user types in. So, ins-, in here, we're going to read a strain. And in order
用户键入。所以，INS-，在这里，我们要读一首曲子。按顺序排列
to do that, we need an IO object because there is another function, another method,
为此，我们需要一个IO对象，因为还有另一个函数、另一个方法
called in-strain. Okay. And so this will renew this string. And return to string.
被称为“in-straint”。好吧。所以这会更新这根弦。然后返回到字符串。
And to make sure that we get the nice output let's concatenate on to that string
为了确保我们得到好的输出，让我们连接到该字符串
a new line. So, this is just to. When it prints this string back out it will be
一条新的路线。所以这只是为了。当它将此字符串重新打印出来时，它将
printed on i ts own line. So, let's try compiling this, And steak. It compiles,
印在自己的行上。那么，让我们试着把这个整理一下，然后吃牛排。它会编译，
And now we can run spin. Remember the bang command in UNIX runs the previous command
现在我们可以开始旋转了。请记住，UNIX中的bang命令运行前面的命令
that began with the same letters. And now the program runs and it waits. Cause it's
都是以相同的字母开头的。现在程序运行，它在等待。因为这是
waiting for me to type something. And if I type it type in one it prints back one and
等着我打点什么。如果我把它打进去，它会把它打印回来，然后
if I type in 42 it gives me back 42. And so now The next thing we need to talk
如果我输入42，它会返回42。所以现在我们要谈的下一件事
about is how to convert strings into integers, because if we're going to do a
关于如何将字符串转换为整数，因为如果我们要做一个
factorial, we want to work on integers and not strings. And at the moment we're just
阶乘，我们希望处理整数而不是字符串。而此时此刻我们只是
reading and writing strings. So, there is a library written in cool that does
读写字符串。所以，有一个用Cool编写的库可以
conversion between integers and strings. And we're going to give the main class
整数和字符串之间的转换。我们要给主要班级
here the functionality of that class. Which is called A2I for ASCII to integer.
这里是该类的功能。它被称为A2I，用于将ASCII转换为整数。
And that defines a bunch of methods, that can convert between strings and integers.
这定义了一系列方法，可以在字符串和整数之间进行转换。
So let's add those, commands in here. So here, here's our string. That we've read
那么让我们在这里添加这些命令。所以这里，这是我们的线。我们已经读过了
in. And what we want to do now is to, convert this into an integer. So let me
在……里面。我们现在要做的是，把它转换成一个整数。所以让我
just add a couple of parens here. So there's our string, okay? And now we're
只需在这里添加几个括号即可。所以这就是我们的线，好吗？现在我们是
going to invoke. On that the method I'm sorry we're going to call on that the
我要召唤。关于这个方法，我很抱歉我们要调用
function the method, A to I. Okay? And let's just double check here that we've
函数的方法，从A到I，好吗？让我们再检查一遍我们有没有
got friends in the right place. So that's the argument to A2I. Now, we recall that
在正确的地方交到了朋友。这就是A2I的论点。现在，我们回想起
when we have a dispatch to a method and it's just sitting by itself with not
当我们有一个方法的派单，而它只是自己坐着不管的时候
object, it's dispatched to the self object. And the self object is the object
对象，则将其调度到Self对象。自我客体就是客体
of the current class that we're in. In this case the main object, which has
我们现在所在的班级。在本例中，主对象具有
inherited the A2I methods, And so the A2I functions should be defined in there. Now
继承了A2I方法，所以应该在那里定义A2I函数。现在
we have an integer. And we can do something with that integer if we like.
我们有一个整数。如果我们愿意，我们可以用这个整数做点什么。
So, let's add some more [inaudible] here and let's just say we add just one to the
所以，让我们在这里再加一些[听不见的]，假设我们只加一个到
integer. Okay. And then once we're done with our integer. Whatever operation it is
整数。好吧。然后一旦我们处理完整数。不管是什么手术
that we want to do with the integer we need to convert it back to a string so
我们想要对整数执行此操作，我们需要将其转换回字符串，因此
that we can print it out. An there's an inverse function I2A that will do. So, I
我们可以把它打印出来。有一个反函数i2a就行了。所以，我
don't know if we have all the parens in the right places at this point. So,
我不知道现在我们是否把所有的父母都放在了正确的位置。所以,
let's just check. Yes. That looks like that should work. So this will, read in a
让我们来检查一下。是。看起来这应该行得通。所以这份遗嘱，读一读
string, convert, convert it to an integer, add one to it convert it back to a string,
字符串，转换，转换成整数，加一再转换回字符串，
concatenate on a new line, and print it out. Now let's see if all that actually
连接在新行上，然后将其打印出来。现在让我们看看这一切是否真的
works, so let's run the compiler and we have a problem here. It says that we have
工作，所以让我们运行编译器，我们在这里有一个问题。上面说我们有
an undefined class A to I. And the reason is, we didn't supply the code for A2I. So
一个未定义的A类到I类，原因是，我们没有提供A2I的代码。所以
if we look in our directory here, we'll see I've already copied in the class file
如果我们查看这里的目录，就会发现我已经复制了类文件
for A2I. And I encourage you to go and look at that code. It's actually
给A2I的。我鼓励你们去看看这段代码。它实际上是
interesting code to see how the conversions are written in COOL.
看看转换是如何用Cool编写的很有趣的代码。
But now we need to talk about how to compile a program that uses a library, And
但现在我们需要讨论如何编写使用库的程序，以及
the way you do it is very simple. You just list all the class files on the command
你做这件事的方法很简单。您只需列出命令中的所有类文件
line when you call up the compiler. And it will read them all in and treat them as a
当您调用编译器时，行。它会把它们全部读进去，并把它们当作
single program. So in this case we compile, compile fact together with A2I.
单一程序。所以在这种情况下，我们编译，编译FACT和A2I一起。
And that complies. And then we can run it. [sound]. And now, if I type in three, it
这也符合我们的要求。然后我们就可以运行它了。[声音]。现在，如果我输入三个字，它
prints four. And if I type in one, it prints two. And so the program seems to be
打印了四张。如果我输入一个，它会打印两个。所以这个项目看起来
working. And now we're almost ready to write our factorial function. So what do
在工作。现在我们几乎准备好编写阶乘函数了。那么，我们该怎么做呢？
we want to do in factorial? Well, we want to do something other than just adding
我们想做阶乘吗？嗯，我们想做的不只是添加
one. Instead, we want to call, our special function factorial. So let's insert a call
一。相反，我们希望调用我们的特殊函数factorial。那么让我们插入一个呼叫
to factorial in here. Okay, and let's get rid of the plus one. And then let's check
到这里的阶乘。好的，让我们去掉加在一起的那个。然后让我们检查一下
that we have all the parens that we need. So we need to close off the, the A2I call,
我们有我们需要的所有父母。所以我们需要关闭A2I电话，
the factorial call, The I2A call. And then that last one should be the out string
阶乘调用，i2a调用。然后最后一个应该是输出字符串
call, And it is, Okay. So now we can add a method fact to this class, And fact is
打个电话，就是了，好的。所以现在我们可以向这个类添加一个方法事实，事实是
gonna take an integer argument. So we need a parameter here, And it's type is in
我要接受一个整数参数。所以我们这里需要一个参数，它的类型是
force. And the whole thing is gonna return an integer. And then we have body of our
武力。整个过程会返回一个整数。然后我们就有了我们的身体
function, And probably a good idea here, just to make sure that we got this much
函数，这里可能是个好主意，只是为了确保我们得到这么多
right, to do something simple. So let's just try to make a function that returns
对，做点简单的事。所以让我们试着创建一个函数，该函数返回
one more than it's argument. So this will do exactly the same thing that we had
比它的论点多了一个。所以这将会做和我们之前做过的完全一样的事情
before and let's just confirm that, that is working. So EW compile with the A2I
在此之前，让我们确认一下，这是有效的。因此，我们使用A2I进行编译
library and now we have a syntax error. And we see that I forgot the closing
库，现在我们有一个语法错误。我们看到我忘了结案陈词
semicolon here for the method. Remember the, the, class body is a list of methods,
在这里用分号表示该方法。记住，类主体是一个方法列表，
and each method is terminated by a semicolon, Must try compiling that again.
并且每个方法都以分号结尾，则必须再次尝试编译。
Now it compiles. Let's run it. We type in four gives a spec five. Alright, So looks
现在它可以编译了。让我们运行它。我们输入4给出规范5。好的，所以看起来
right we're ready now to actually right the code for factorial. And this is gonna
好了，我们现在已经准备好实际纠正阶乘的代码了。而这将会是
be anti climactic because it's actually a very simple code if we write it
令人沮丧的是，如果我们编写它，它实际上是一个非常简单的代码
recursively. So let's do that. So how's that going to work? Well, everybody knows
递归地。那我们就这么做吧。那么这是怎么回事呢？嗯，大家都知道
the definition by Hardy Hope. If I is equal to zero then the factorial of zero
哈代·霍普的定义。如果i等于零，那么零的阶乘
is one. And we have a keyword there then one, otherwise the factorial is going to
就是其中之一。我们在那里有一个关键字，然后是一个，否则阶乘将会
be I times, the factorial of I minus one. Right, and then if statements in
就是i乘以i减一的阶乘。对，然后如果语句中
[inaudible] always end in the keyword [inaudible] so it's an if then else
[听不到]总是以关键字[听不到]结尾，所以它是IF THEN ELSE
[inaudible] construct. And that is actually the entire definition. So now we
[听不见]构造。这实际上就是整个定义。所以现在我们
should have a program that actually computes factorial, it compiles, so now
应该有一个真正计算阶乘的程序，它会编译，所以现在
let's run it. So factorial of three is six. And factorial of six, is 720 and that
让我们运行它。所以3的阶乘是6。6的阶乘是720
looks right. And if we try it one more time with a bigger number, we get a, we
看起来是对的。如果我们用一个更大的数字再试一次，我们会得到一个，我们
get a large number, we think that's probably correct. And so, anyway our
得到一个大数目，我们认为这可能是正确的。所以，不管怎样，我们的
factorial function, is working. So, now let's come back here, and just as an
阶乘函数，起作用了。所以，现在让我们回到这里，作为一个
exercise, let's rewrite this code iteratively. So instead of using a
练习，让我们迭代地重写这段代码。因此，与其使用
recursive function, let's write it using a loop. And in order to that [inaudible]
递归函数，让我们使用循环来编写它。为了[听不见]
gonna get rid of that code. What are we going to need? Well, we're going to need
我要去掉那个密码。我们需要什么？嗯，我们需要
an accumulator here. We're going to need a, a local variable that we can use to
这里有个蓄电池。我们需要一个，一个局部变量，我们可以用它来
accumulate the results of the factorial computation. And the way you declare local
累加阶乘计算的结果。以及你声明本地化的方式
variables in [inaudible] is with [inaudible] Statements, or naudibl
[不可听]中的变量带有[不可听]语句，或不可听
expressions. So we're gonna have, let's call this, variable fact, for the, result
表情。因此，我们将有，让我们称之为，可变事实，对于结果
of factorial. And notice here that I can have a variable that has the same name as
阶乘的。请注意，这里我可以有一个与以下名称相同的变量
the function. And the programming language, [inaudible] will not get
函数。和编程语言，[听不见]将不会得到
confused about that, Because variables and functions, play different roles. So we'll
对此感到困惑，因为变量和函数，扮演着不同的角色。所以我们会
have the factorial fact, excuse me, it's of type Int, and we do initialize it to
有阶乘事实，打扰一下，它是Int类型的，我们确实将它初始化为
one. Alright, so that multiplication will work. I think that the default for
一。好的，这样乘法就行了。我认为默认情况下
integers is to be initialized to zero and that would not be good if we're going to
整数要初始化为零，如果我们要
be multiplying up fact with other with other numbers. Alright, so then the, a let
将事实与其他数字相乘。好的，那么，那就是，让
has two parts. It has the variable or variables that you are declaring. This
有两个部分。它包含您正在声明的一个或多个变量。这
could actually be a list of variables. We'll only have one this time. And then it
可能实际上是一个变量列表。这次我们只要一个。然后它
has a body. The, the expression or the computation in which the fact variable is
有一具身体。事实变量为的事实变量的表达式或计算
available. And what do we want to do? So, I think we're gonna need to have this be a
有空的。那我们想做什么呢？所以，我想我们需要把这件事
statement block 'cause we're gonna need to have more than one statement in the
挡路语句，因为我们需要在
sequence. And we'll see why in just a minute. But then we wanna have a loop. And
序列。稍后我们再来看看原因。但是我们想要一个循环。和
so what is our loop going to do? Well, we're gonna say while I is not equal to
那么我们的循环要做什么呢？好吧，我们要说的是，虽然我不能
zero. What do we, and what do we need to do the opening for the loop body the
零。我们应该做什么，我们需要做什么来打开循环体
opening keyword is called loop. [sound]. And now, I think we're going to need
开始关键字称为循环。[声音]。现在，我想我们需要
another statement block here. So let's open up a block. We're gonna probably need
另一份声明请单击此处的挡路。那么让我们开一家挡路吧。我们可能需要
to do more than one thing. The first thing we want to do is we want to have fact. Be
做不止一件事。我们想要做的第一件事是我们想要有事实。BE
fact times I, so we know that I is not zero so we need to multiply the current
事实乘以I，所以我们知道I不是零，所以我们需要乘以电流
value of I into fact to accumulate the result and then we want to subtract one
将i的值转化为事实来累加结果，然后我们要减去1
from I and notice that the assignment statement in cool is this backwards arrow.
注意，COOL中的赋值语句是这个向后箭头。
That's how you do assignment. It's also how you do initialization. So,
你就是这样做任务的。这也是您进行初始化的方式。所以,
initialization and assignment look the same. Then we can close off our statement
初始化和赋值看起来是一样的。然后我们就可以结账了
block. Okay, so the body of a while loop is always a single expression. In this
挡路。好的，While循环的主体总是一个表达式。在这里面
case, that expression is a block that consists of two statements. [sound] And
在这种情况下，该表达式是由两个语句组成的挡路。[声音]和
then we can close the loop. And the closing for a loop is the pool key word.
然后我们就可以关闭环路了。循环的结尾是POOL关键字。
And then now we're in a statement block, so this has to end with a semicolon.
现在我们在挡路声明中，所以必须以分号结束。
Notice the statement block up there from the let, And now we want the result of the
请注意上面来自LET的挡路语句，现在我们需要
let block, or the let expression, to be factorial. So whatever the, whatever we
让挡路或let的表达成为阶乘。所以不管什么，不管我们
got out of the while loop, whatever we computed in the while loop, we want that
摆脱了WHILE循环，无论我们在WHILE循环中计算了什么，我们都希望
to be the result of the entire let expression. [sound] so that's the last
作为整个let表达式的结果。[声音]所以这是最后一次了
statement of our blog. Remember the last statement of a statement blog, is the
我们博客的声明。记住声明博客的最后一句话，是
value of the blog. The body of the led is the, the result of the led, so fact will
博客的价值。发光二极管的本体是发光二极管的结果，所以事实也是如此。
also be result of the whole led statements, it's just the result of the
也是整个led语句的结果，这只是
statement blog. And since the body of the, factorial method itself is just the led
声明博客。由于阶乘方法的主体本身就是主导的
expression, fact will be the result of the whole thing. And so this, if we've
表达，事实将是整个事情的结果。所以这个，如果我们
written, haven't made any mistakes, should be an iterative version of factorial. So,
写的，没有任何错误，应该是阶乘的迭代版本。所以,
let's compile this. And amazingly it complies on the first try. And now let's
让我们编译这段代码。令人惊讶的是，它在第一次尝试时就符合要求。现在让我们
run it. [sound] And whoa! It actually works. So we got six. And let's just do
运行它。[声音]哇哦！它确实起作用了。所以我们有六个人。我们就这么做吧
one more test, to see that, to convince ourselves that, things are working
再来一次测试，看看，说服我们自己，事情正在进行中
reasonably well, and they are. Now, let me just point out, one, common, mistake, that
相当不错，他们确实是这样。现在，让我指出，一个常见的错误，
you can easily make, and, that I make when I haven't written cool programs for a
你可以很容易地做，而且，当我还没有写很酷的程序的时候，你可以很容易地做这件事。
little while. If you're a C or programmer or a Java programmer, you might, think
一会儿就好。如果您是一名C或程序员或Java程序员，您可能会认为
about, writing assignments, like this. So I just use the equal sign to write
关于，写作业，像这样。所以我只是用等号来写
assignment. That looks completely fine if you're, if you're familiar with those
任务。如果你是，如果你熟悉那些，那看起来完全没问题
languages, or used to programming in those languages. And now, let's see what happens
语言，或者习惯于用这些语言编程。现在，让我们看看会发生什么
when we try to compile this. Oh, it compiles just fine. And then what happens
当我们试图编译这个的时候。哦，它编译得很好。然后会发生什么
when we try to run it. Well it runs [inaudible] input so let's give it input
当我们试图运行它的时候。好的，它运行[听不见]输入，所以让我们给它输入
and. Then we see that we've run out of heat. And that looks like an infinite
和。然后我们发现我们的热量用完了。这看起来像是一个无限大的
loop. So we're going around and around the loop And consuming memory for some reason.
循环。因此，出于某种原因，我们在循环中循环并消耗内存。
And we'll, we '[laugh] get to that much later in the class. Why, why this loop
我们会在课上晚些时候讲到这一点。为什么，为什么是这个环路
actually ends up consuming memory. But, clearly, we don't have enough memory, in
实际上最终会消耗内存。但是，很明显，我们没有足够的内存，在
the loop, and, and eventually we run out. And so, so that's a sure sign Of an
循环，然后，最终我们就用完了。所以，这是一个明确的信号
infinite look. So what is going on here? Well the thing is that equals. Equals
无限的眼神。那么这里到底是怎么回事呢？问题是这等于。等于
operator in cool is the comparison operators. [inaudible] Well we compared I
COOL中的运算符是比较运算符。[听不见]嗯，我们比较了一下
with O and that returns a boullion. So these are perfectly valid cool
加上O，它会返回一个大球。所以这些都是非常有效的，酷毙了
expressions. They just happen to be boullions. So, you don't ever actually I
表情。它们只是碰巧是巨石。所以，你不会真的
or factorial in this program. Your just comparing fact with factoid body and I
或者这个程序中的阶乘。你只是拿事实和我的肉体做比较
with I minus one and the program is perfectly happy to do that. It just
我减一，程序非常乐意这样做。它只是
doesn't compute the factorial function. And it never terminates, because I never
不计算阶乘函数。它永远不会结束，因为我从来没有
reaches zero. So that concludes our factorial example. And we'll do one more
达到零。我们的阶乘示例到此结束。我们会再做一次
example next time of a more complicated, of a, of a cool program with some
下一次更复杂的示例，一个很酷的程序，有一些
non-trivial data structures.
非常重要的数据结构。